Guide to the Wilfred Thomason Grenfell Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Wilfred Thomason Grenfell papers
1812-1986
MS 254
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
32.25
(76 boxes, 1 folio)
The papers consist of correspondence, diaries, ships' logs, notebooks, writings, speeches, and legal and financial papers documenting Wilfred T. Grenfell's medical missionary work in Labrador, particularly for the years 1930-1940. Also included are scattered papers of the Royal National Mission to Deep Sea Fishermen and the Grenfell Associations, containing correspondence, minutes, financial records and reports (1893-1949). The small amount of papers of Ann MacClanahan Grenfell, his wife, consist largely of correspondence related to the Grenfell Association and two travel diaries (1924-1926). Grenfell's correspondence, notebooks and diaries are a valuable source for Labrador and Newfoundland history, as well as economic and social conditions between 1892, when he committed himself to missionary work in Labrador, and his death in 1940. There are also family papers relating to both the Grenfell and MacClanahan families. Providing an overall view of Grenfell's life are twenty-one scrapbooks (1893-1939) and a collection of nearly 10,500 photographs of life in Newfoundland and Labrador (1890-1940), of various missions and views of the Grenfell's travels to other parts of the world (1891-1932).
Grenfell, Wilfred Thomason, Sir, 1865-1940
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Wilfred T. Grenfell, Jr., Kinloch Pascoe Grenfell, and Rosamond Grenfell Shaw, 1943-1980; Wilfred T. Grenfell, Jr., 1988 and 1990; Janet G. Kahler, 1987; David S. Ashdown, 1990; and Harry G. Toland, 1991; Graduate Theological Union, 1996; and Ann T. Babine, 1996.
Existence and Location of Copies
Scrapbooks, diaries, ships' logs, and notebooks are available on microfilm (7,112 frames on 7 reels, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM80.
Arrangement
The papers are divided into fifteen series and five additions, organized as follows: I. CORRESPONDENCE. II. DIARIES. III. SHIPS' LOGS. IV. NOTEBOOKS. V. WRITINGS. VI. PUBLIC SPEAKING. VII. LEGAL AND FINANCIAL PAPERS. VIII. ANNE (MACCLANAHAN) GRENFELL. IX. ROYAL NATIONAL MISSION TO DEEP SEA FISHERMEN. X. GRENFELL ASSOCIATIONS. XI. THIRD PARTY. XII. FAMILY PAPERS. XIII. MEMORABILIA. XIV. PHOTOGRAPHS. XV. OVERSIZE
Scope and Contents
The Wilfred T. Grenfell Papers contain primarily the personal and professional papers of Sir Wilfred Thomason Grenfell, medical missionary to Newfoundland and Labrador. From 1892 on, Grenfell devoted his life to his Labrador work, and both his professional and personal papers reflect his dedication to this work. Both deal with economic and social problems in Labrador and with the remedies Grenfell sought to administer through the work of his Grenfell Associations. In addition, both are infused with Grenfell's strong religious beliefs, which demanded action to better man's condition.
The papers are divided into fifteen series and five additions, organized as follows: I. CORRESPONDENCE. II. DIARIES. III. SHIPS' LOGS. IV. NOTEBOOKS. V. WRITINGS. VI. PUBLIC SPEAKING. VII. LEGAL AND FINANCIAL PAPERS. VIII. ANNE (MACCLANAHAN) GRENFELL. IX. ROYAL NATIONAL MISSION TO DEEP SEA FISHERMEN. X. GRENFELL ASSOCIATIONS. XI. THIRD PARTY. XII. FAMILY PAPERS. XIII. MEMORABILIA. XIV. PHOTOGRAPHS. XV. OVERSIZE.
At the beginning of the folder list for each series is a description which gives more information about the contents and arrangements of that series.
The papers are especially useful for studying aspects of Newfoundland and Labrador history, economy and sociology between 1892 and 1940. Letters to his family provide detailed narratives of his life and work in Labrador, as well as frequent expressions of his religious and political views. In general, the papers stress W.T. Grenfell's role as a missionary rather than his role as a doctor. The administrative and financial aspects of the Grenfell Association permeate the entire collection, while the number of medical papers is surprisingly small. Almost half the collection dates between 1930 and 1940.
There is some material, mostly correspondence, dating from Grenfell's childhood and education. However, his volunteer service as a major with the Harvard Surgical Unit in France during World War I is the only other relatively well documented period of his life. See outgoing correspondence 1941-15 (Series I), and his diary (Series II), writings (Series V) and memorabilia (Series XIII) for material regarding his World War I experiences.
At the beginning of his career in Newfoundland, Grenfell worked for the R.N.M.D.S.F. (Royal National Mission To Deep Sea Fishermen), a British charitable organization devoted to the welfare of British sailors of the North Sea and Grand Banks fleets, and served as a justice of the peace. Many of his administrative papers (Series I, outgoing), and a smaller amount of material from other R.N.M.D.S.F. officials (Series X) are preserved here, as well as some legal papers (Series VII). All of these provide a picture of the organization, spiced with the personality conflicts endemic to any organization, and of the poverty, unemployment, malnutrition, and other economic and social problems of Newfoundland and Labrador which the R.N.M.D.S.F. was attempting to rectify.
Papers relating to the Grenfell Association are also an important source of information on Newfoundland and Labrador. Grenfell founded this organization in 1912 to help him raise funds for his Labrador work, administer those funds and the newly founded facilities, and attract volunteers ("Wops" or "With-out-pay") to the area as teachers, doctors, and agricultural advisors. In the process of administering the Grenfell Association, W.T. Grenfell came in contact with important government officials of Newfoundland and Canada, and with many major philanthropists. As a result there is a fair amount of correspondence (Series I) from figures such as William Lyon MacKenzie King and the governors of Newfoundland and a lesser amount concerning various philanthropical activities from Henry Ford, John Rockefeller, Albert Schweitzer and others.
Aside from purely administrative and philanthropical matters, W.T. Grenfell involved himself in numerous projects connected in one way or another with the welfare of Labrador. Among these was the establishment of a reindeer herd for transportation and nutrition purposes, and the use of cellulose acetate in tuberculosis sanataria. (See series I, V, XI, XIV)
Grenfell adamantly believed in the positive part religion should play in the eradication of suffering from the modern world. His writings and speeches (Series V, VI) promote temperance societies in industrial countries and encourage support for basic medical, educational, and economic aid to the poorer nations. He often expressed the view that the poor could help themselves if they were given employment rather than charity. Through the Grenfell Association he promoted the establishment of cottage industries as well as larger projects such as sawmills in Newfoundland and Labrador.
A particular strength of the Grenfell Papers is the large photograph collection. Almost 10,500 photographs taken by W.T. Grenfell, his family and colleagues provide a visual record of Newfoundland and Labrador between 1890 and 1940, and of Eskimo and Indian inhabitants and European settlers. Interesting from a biographical standpoint is a long series of photographs stretching from W.T. Grenfell's grandparents to his grandchildren which closely detail his own life from 1873 to 1940 and that of his wife and children.
Throughout the papers W.T. Grenfell and his family are referred to by their initials, a practice followed by them in their correspondence and in annotations on photographs. The abbreviations used are:
W.T.G. Wilfred Thomason Grenfell or Wilfred Thomason Grenfell, Jr.
A.E.G. Anne E.G (MacClanahan) Grenfell
A.B. the same
K.P.G. Kinloch Pascoe Grenfell
R.L.G. Rosamond Loveday (Grenfell) Shaw
N.K.G. Nora K. Grenfell, wife of W.T. Grenfell, Jr.
A.S.G. Algernon Sidney Grenfell
J.G.G. Jane Georgiana (Hutchinson) Grenfell
A.G.G. Algernon G. Grenfell
The vast bulk of the papers were given to the Yale University Library by W. T. Grenfell's three children, W.T. Grenfell, Jr., Kinloch Pascoe Grenfell, and Rosamond (Grenfell) Shaw over the period 1943-1980.
Other related collections in Manuscripts and Archives are The New England Grenfell Association Papers (Mss. #1200) and the Elizabeth Paige Harris Papers (Mss. #771). Elizabeth (Paige) Harris was a volunteer worker for the Grenfell Association in White Bay, Newfoundland, for several years, and thereafter worked occasionally on fund raising and other matters in the United States. See also the papers of the Yale Grenfell Association in Yale Archives (YRG 40-A-16).
In Series I, VIII, and IX an * before the name indicates that a folder contains 10 or more items for that individual.
Biographical / Historical
Wilfred Grenfell was a medical missionary to Newfoundland and Labrador from 1892-1940. He was an author and a member of Royal National Mission to Deep Sea Fishermen. Grenfell established the Labrador Medical Mission and the International Grenfell Association.
Medical care -- Canada; Missionaries' spouses; Missionaries -- Newfoundland and Labrador -- Labrador; Missionaries -- Newfoundland and Labrador; Missionaries, Medical; Canada; Labrador (N.L.) -- Economic conditions; Labrador (N.L.) -- Social conditions; Newfoundland and Labrador; Diaries; Ships' papers; Missionaries; Alderdice, Frederick C., 1872-1936; Allardyce, William Lamond, 1861-1930; Anderson, David Murray, 1874-1936; Ashdown, Cecil; Baden-Powell of Gilwell, Robert Stephenson Smyth Baden-Powell, Baron, 1857-1941; Birdeye, Clarence, 1886-1956; Bols, Louis Jean, 1867-1930; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925; Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957; Danforth, William Henry, 1870-; Davidson, Walter Edward, 1859-1923; Forsyth, Chester Hume, 1881-; Grenfell, Anne, 1885-1938; Grenfell, Wilfred Thomason, Sir, 1865-1940; Halsey, Jesse, 1882-; Halsey, Lionel, 1872-1949; Hare, H. Mather; Harris, C. Alexander, Sir (Charles Alexander), 1855-1947; King, William Lyon Mackenzie, 1874-1950; Lothian, Philip Henry Kerr, Marquis of, 1882-1940; MacGregor, William, 1846-1919; Mayo, William James, 1861-1939; Morris, Edward Patrick, 1859-1935; Mountevans, Edward Ratcliffe Garth Russell Evans, Baron, 1880-1957; Murray, Herbert Harley, 1829-1904; O'Brien, John Terence Nicolls, 1830-1903; Patenaude, Esioff-Léon, 1875-1963; Patey, Reuben; Peary, Robert E. (Robert Edwin), 1856-1920; Rockefeller, John D., Jr. (John Davison), 1874-1960; Roosevelt, Edith Kermit Carow, 1861-1948; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Ryerson, Knowles Augustus, 1892-1990; Schweitzer, Albert, 1875-1965; Sheard, Abraham; Stirling, William R.; Strathcona and Mount Royal, Donald Alexander Smith, Baron, 1820-1914; Treves, Frederick, Sir, 1st baron., 1853-1923; Wallace, R. H. (Raymond H.); Walwyn, Humphrey Thomas, 1879-1957; Wheelock, Louis; Whiteway, William Vallance, Sir, 1828-1908; MacClanahan family; International Grenfell Association; Royal National Mission to Deep Sea Fishermen
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1870-1940, undated; Series I; 4 linear feet (10 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is divided into two sections, Outgoing and Incoming. Since letters to Anne E.M. Grenfell were sometimes answered by W.T. Grenfell and vice versa, her correspondence (Series VIII) should be consulted in conjunction with this series.
  Outgoing contains letters written by W.T. Grenfell on both personal and business matters. The letters are arranged chronologically with undated letters filed at the end of the section. While there are letters for earlier periods in Grenfell's life, letters from the decade 1930-1940 comprise almost half of the section.
  Incoming is composed of letters received by W.T. Grenfell. It includes all business and family letters, but excludes printed invitations, which are found in Series XIII. The letters are arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent, and letters by the same correspondent have been arranged chronologically. Correspondence from unidentified sources follows at the end of the section, in chronological order. Letters from especially noted individuals, such as Albert Schweitzer, along with those of major correspondents (10 or more items), are foldered separately by the name of the correspondent and placed at the end of the appropriate letter of the alphabet. Letters from government officials are to be found under the country and office they represent, e.g. Newfoundland, Governor's Office. Correspondence from R.N.M.D.S.F. and Grenfell Association workers is to be found under the name of the individual.
  - Outgoing
    - 1870-1901 (Box 1, Folder 1-10)
    - 1900 July 6-15: letterbook (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1900 July 26-November 3: letterbook (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1901 December 10-15: letterbook (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1902-1910 July 24 (Box 1, Folder 14-27)
    - 1910 July 26-[1923?] (Box 2, Folder 28-66)
    - [ca. 1923-1926]-1931 (Box 3, Folder 67-94)
    - 1932 January-1938 August (Box 4, Folder 95-127)
    - 1938 September-1940 Oct, undated (Box 5, Folder 128-167)
  - Incoming
    - Ab-Az (Box 6, Folder 168-172)
      correspondence
    - A (unidentified) (Box 6, Folder 173)
    - Alderdice, Hon. Frederick C., 1932, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 174)
    - Allardyce, Sir William, 1927-1928 (Box 6, Folder 174)
    - Ashdown, Cecil(*), 1927-1940 (Box 6, Folder 175)
    - Bad-By (Box 6, Folder 176-188)
    - B (unidentified) (Box 6, Folder 189)
    - Baden-Powell, Lt. General Sir Robert S.S., 1911 (Box 6, Folder 190)
    - Bartholomey, Dora de (Mme.), 1916 (Box 6, Folder 190)
    - Birdseye, Clarence, 1914,1939 (Box 6, Folder 191)
    - Bols, Lt. General Sir Louis J., 1927 (Box 6, Folder 191)
    - Bryan, William Jennings, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 191)
    - Byrd, Admiral Richard E., 1939 (Box 6, Folder 191)
    - Cab-Cushm (Box 6, Folder 192-202)
    - C (unidentified) (Box 6, Folder 203)
    - Carnegie, Louise (Mrs. Andrew), 1939-1930, undated (Box 6, Folder 204)
    - Dak-Day (Box 6, Folder 205-207)
    - Dea-Du (Box 7, Folder 208-211)
    - Danforth, William H., 1934, 1938-1940 (Box 7, Folder 212)
    - Ea-Ew (Box 7, Folder 213-214)
    - Fa-Fy (Box 7, Folder 215-220)
    - Forsyth, C. H., 1933, 1937-1938 (Box 7, Folder 221)
    - Ga-Gu (Box 7, Folder 222-227)
    - Gray, Jennie, 1910 (Box 7, Folder 228)
    - Grenfell, Algernon G.(*), 1877-1934 (Box 7, Folder 229)
    - Grenfell, Aline(*), 1909 (Box 7, Folder 229)
    - Grenfell, Anne M.(*), [1919], [1927],1931, 1936-1938 (Box 7, Folder 230-231)
    - Grenfell, Arthur-Grenfell, Francis, 1907-1927 (Box 7, Folder 232)
    - Grenfell, Jane-Grenfell, William, 1907-1938, undated (Box 7, Folder 233)
    - Grenfell Association, 1910 (Box 7, Folder 234)
    - Grenfell Association of Newfoundland, 1921, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 234)
    - Grenfell Foundation, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 234)
    - Grey, Albert Henry George Grey, 4th Earl, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 235)
    - Ha-Hu (Box 7, Folder 236-245)
    - H (unidentified) (Box 7, Folder 246)
    - Halsey, Jesse, 1936-1939, undated (Box 7, Folder 247)
    - Halsey, Admiral Sir Lionel, [1937?] (Box 7, Folder 248)
    - Hare, H. Mather, 1905-1911 (Box 7, Folder 249)
    - I (Box 7, Folder 250)
    - Jac-Ju (Box 8, Folder 251-254)
    - Ka-Kr (Box 8, Folder 255-259)
    - King, Rt. Hon. William Lyon MacKenzie(*), 1905-1940, undated (Box 8, Folder 260-262)
    - La-Ly (Box 8, Folder 263-267)
    - L (unidentified) (Box 8, Folder 268)
    - Lothian, Philip Henry Kerr, 11th Marquess of, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 269)
    - Mab-My (Box 8, Folder 270-278)
    - M (unidentified) (Box 8, Folder 279)
    - Mayo, Dr. William J., 1921, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 280)
    - Mountevans, Admiral Edward R.G.R. Evans, 1st Baron, 1914 (Box 8, Folder 280)
    - Na-Nu (Box 8, Folder 281-284)
    - N (unidentified) (Box 8, Folder 285)
    - Newfoundland, Attorney General's Office, 1903-1910 (Box 8, Folder 286)
    - Newfoundland, Bishop of, 1895, 1899, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 286)
    - Newfoundland, Colonial Secretary's Office, 1902-1910, 1932, undated (Box 8, Folder 287)
    - Newfoundland, Customs, 1910, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 288)
    - Newfoundland, Finance Department, 1906-1910 (Box 8, Folder 288)
    - Newfoundland, Governor (Admiral Sir David M. Anderson), 1933 (Box 8, Folder 289)
    - Newfoundland, Governor (Sir W. E. Davidson), 1914-1915 (Box 8, Folder 290)
    - Newfoundland, Governor (Sir C. A. Harris), 1918-1922, undated (Box 8, Folder 291)
    - Newfoundland, Governor (Sir W. MacGregor)(*), 1905-1911 (Box 8, Folder 292)
    - Newfoundland, Governor (Sir H. H. Murray), 1898, undated (Box 8, Folder 293)
    - Newfoundland, Governor (Sir J.T.N. O'Brien)(*), 1894-1995, undated (Box 8, Folder 294)
    - Newfoundland, Governor (Vice-Admiral Sir Humphrey T. Walwyn), 1938 (Box 8, Folder 295)
    - Newfoundland, Governor (Sir Ralph C. Williams), 1910-1911 (Box 8, Folder 296)
    - Newfoundland, High Commissioner's Offices, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 297)
    - Newfoundland, Inspector General's Office, 1895 (Box 8, Folder 297)
    - Newfoundland, Justice, Department of, 1906, 1909-1910 (Box 8, Folder 297)
    - Newfoundland, Marine & Fisheries, Department of, 1905-1907, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 297)
    - Newfoundland, Natural Resources, Department of, 1934-1935, 1939-1940 (Box 8, Folder 297)
    - Newfoundland, General Post Office, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 297)
    - Newfoundland, Prime Minister's Office (Sir E. P. Morris)(*), 1909-1910, undated (Box 9, Folder 298)
    - Newfoundland, Prime Minister's Office (Sir W. V. Whiteway), 1895-1896 (Box 9, Folder 299)
    - Newfoundland, Prime Minister's Office, 1927 (Box 9, Folder 300)
    - Newfoundland, Public Charities, 1910 (Box 9, Folder 301)
    - Newfoundland, Public Health, 1909 (Box 9, Folder 301)
    - Ob-Ox (Box 9, Folder 302-303)
    - Pad-Pu (Box 9, Folder 304-310)
    - P (unidentified) (Box 9, Folder 311)
    - Patenaude, Lt. Governor E. L., 1933 (Box 9, Folder 312)
    - Patey, Reuben(*), 1922, 1939-1940 (Box 9, Folder 312)
    - Peary, Admiral Robert E., 1909 (Box 9, Folder 312)
    - Q (Box 9, Folder 313)
    - Ra-Ru (Box 9, Folder 314-319)
    - Rockefeller, John D., Jr., 1911-1938, undated (Box 9, Folder 320)
    - Roosevelt, Edith K. (Mrs. Theedore), 1926 (Box 9, Folder 320)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore, 1912 (Box 9, Folder 320)
    - Ryerson, Knowles, 1930, 1938-1940 (Box 9, Folder 321)
    - Sai-Sy (Box 9, Folder 322-337)
    - S (unidentified) (Box 10, Folder 338)
    - Schweitzer, Dr. Albert, undated (Box 10, Folder 338a)
    - Sheard, Abraham (Secretary, Royal National Mission to Deep Sea Fishermen)(*), 1912 September-1913 November (Box 10, Folder 339-345)
    - Strathcona and Mount Royal, Donald A. Smith, 1st Baron(*), 1895-1911 (Box 10, Folder 346)
    - Ta-Ty (Box 10, Folder 347-351)
    - Treves, Annie E. (Lady Frederick), 1902, undated (Box 10, Folder 352)
    - Treves, Sir Frederick, 1891-1910, undated (Box 10, Folder 353-354)
    - U (Box 10, Folder 355)
    - V (Box 10, Folder 356)
    - V (unidentified) (Box 10, Folder 357)
    - Wak-Wr (Box 10, Folder 358-367)
    - W (unidentified) (Box 10, Folder 368)
    - Wallace, Raymond H.(*), 1938 February-1940 (Box 10, Folder 369-70)
    - Wheelock, Louis(*), [1935]-1940 (Box 10, Folder 371-372)
    - Y (Box 10, Folder 373)
    - Z (Box 10, Folder 374)
    - Unidentified, 1895-1940, n.d (Box 10, Folder 375)
- DIARIES, 1881-1939; Series II
  General
  The entire series has been microfilmed, patrons must use HM 80, Series II. See inventory for reel numbers.
  - 1881-1925 (Box 11, Folder 1, Reel 1)
  - 1877 (Box 11, Folder 2, Reel 1)
  - 1895 Dec 21-1896 Dec 29 (Box 11, Folder 3, Reel 1)
  - 1897 (Box 11, Folder 4, Reel 1)
  - 1914-1915 (Box 11, Folder 5, Reel 1)
  - 1925 Jun 26-Aug 24 (Box 11, Folder 6, Reel 1)
  - 1929-1930 Jan 5 (Box 11, Folder 7, Reel 1)
  - 1930-1931 Jan 1 (Box 11, Folder 8, Reel 1)
  - 1931 (Box 11, Folder 9, Reel 1)
  - 1931-1932 (Box 12, Folder 10, Reel 1)
  - 1936 Nov 9-1937 Jan 6 (Box 12, Folder 11, Reel 1)
  - 1937 (Box 12, Folder 12, Reel 1)
  - 1938 (Box 12, Folder 13, Reel 2)
  - 1939 (Box 12, Folder 14, Reel 2)
- SHIPS' LOGS, 1896, 1926-1927; Series III
  - Log of the S.S. Sir Donald, 1896 March-Dec, undated (Box 13, Folder 1-8, Reel 2)
  - Log of the S.S. Strathcona II, 1926 August (Box 13, Folder 9, Reel 2)
  - Log of the S.S. Strathcona II: typescript draft, 1926 (Box 13, Folder 10, Reel 2)
  - Log [of the S.S. Strathcona II]: partial holograph draft, [ca. 1926-1927] (Box 13, Folder 11, Reel 2)
  - Log of the S.S. Strathcona II: two typescript drafts, Log no. 1, 1927 July 5, n. (Box 13, Folder 12, Reel 2)
  - Log of the S.S. Strathcona II: typescript draft, Log no. 2, 1927 July 21 (Box 13, Folder 13, Reel 2)
  - Log of the S.S. Strathcona II: typescript draft, third trip, 1927 (Box 13, Folder 14, Reel 2)
- NOTEBOOKS, 1885-1940; Series IV
  - Medical
    - "Medical Cases", [ca. 1885-1889] (Box 14, Folder 1, Reel 2)
    - "Surgical notes on Cases", [ca. 1885-1889] (Box 14, Folder 2, Reel 2)
    - Notes on anatomy, [pre-1886] (Box 14, Folder 3, Reel 2)
    - Untitled, [1913-1935?] (Box 14, Folder 4, Reel 2)
    - Includes notes on faith and losses at sea near Labrador in 1892, [ca. 1937] (Box 14, Folder 5, Reel 2)
    - "Notes-M.B. with Dr. Maybury", undated (Box 14, Folder 6, Reel 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Commonplace book re Newfoundland and Labrador, [ca. 1891] (Box 14, Folder 7, Reel 2)
    - Commonplace book re Eskimo lore and language, [1895-1896?] (Box 15, Folder 8, Reel 2)
    - Recordbook of populations, labor, and medical statistics re mission stations on the Newfoundland and Labrador coasts, [ca. 1895-1931: (Box 15, Folder 9, Reel 3)
    - Minutebook of a Cooperative Movement meeting, includes occasional medical notes, 1900 January 25 (Box 15, Folder 10, Reel 3)
    - Recordbook re St. Anthony Men's Bible class, 1910 January 31-June 10 (Box 15, Folder 11, Reel 3)
    - Commonplace book of addresses and notes on various topics, [ca. 1920-1925] (Box 15, Folder 12, Reel 3)
    - Commonplace book re travels in Egypt, Palestine, Persia, India, Japan, [1924-1925] (Box 15, Folder 13, Reel 3)
    - Dictionary notebook re various subjects, [1926-1939] (Box 15, Folder 14, Reel 3)
    - Commonplace book on various subjects, [ca. 1933] (Box 15, Folder 15, Reel 3)
    - Commonplace book re American and international politics, [1933-1934] (Box 15, Folder 16, Reel 3)
    - "Notes on Labradorite Machine", [ca. 1935] (Box 16, Folder 17, Reel 3)
    - Philosophical jottings, 1940 (Box 16, Folder 18, Reel 3)
    - notes on aid to cooperatives, voluntary hospital contributions, adaptation of shrubs and trees, [ca. 1940] (Box 16, Folder 19, Reel 3)
    - "Notes for Book on Labrador", undated (Box 16, Folder 20, Reel 3)
    - Commonplace book re history of Labrador, undated (Box 16, Folder 21, Reel 3)
    - Commonplace book re Labrador, includes diary entries re unidentified trip to Montreal, Canada, undated (Box 16, Folder 22, Reel 3)
    - Commonplace book re Labrador history, inhabitants, climate, minerals, fishery, and wildlife, undated (Box 16, Folder 23, Reel 3)
    - Address book including notes on various topics, undated (Box 16, Folder 24, Reel 3)
- WRITINGS, 1888-1940, undated; Series V; 3 linear feet (7 boxes)
  This series contains works written by W.T. Grenfell. It is divided into six sections: Books, Articles and Essays, Pamphlets and Leaflets, Reports, notes, and Other.
  Books consists of drafts and partial drafts, arranged chronologically, for several of Grenfell's books, in particular his autobiography A Labrador Doctor, and his national and political history of Labrador, The Romance of Labrador.